Joseph Konzal Papers
Special Collections Research Center Syracuse University 222 Waverly Ave Syracuse, NY 13244-2010
Joseph Konzal Papers
1939-1962
Special Collections Research Center Syracuse University 222 Waverly Ave Syracuse, NY 13244-2010
Konzal, Joseph, 1905-1994.
0.25 linear ft.
American sculptor. Collection contains correspondence, printed material, photographs of Konzal's work, and three small paintings by the American Sculptor.
2741999
Biographical History
Joseph Konzal (1905-1994) was an American sculptor known for his abstract works in cast metals, wood and found objects. As a professional artist he was active in the Sculptors Guild, based in New York City, and he produced work for the Federal Art Program of the Works Progress Administration. Konzal taught sculpture at several institutions including the Brooklyn Museum Art School, Queens College, Adelphi University and Kent State University, and his work is in the permanent collections of the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Smithsonian Institution in Washington and the Tate Gallery in London, among others.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Joseph Konzal Papers is divided into three series. Original work contains photographs of Konzal's scuplture. Most are black and white though some are in color. This series also contains three of his oil paintings. Published materials contains documents relating to Konzal's art or his teaching. These include reviews, advertisements and correspondence concerning his sculpture. Also included are course catalogs from schools where he taught. Ephemera contains photographs, newspaper clippings and advertisements glued to wooden boards by Joseph Konzal.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged chronologically. Where items are undated, they are placed at the end of the series and retain the original order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Konzal, Joseph, 1905-1994.; Federal Art Project.; Sculptors Guild (New York, N.Y.); Artists -- United States -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States -- 20th century.; Photographs.; Paintings (visual works); Leaflets.; Curricula.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joseph Konzal, 1966.
Inventory
- Original artwork
  - Paintings, oil, untitled, 1927; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Painting, oil, untitled, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographic reproductions of Konzal's work, 1939-1962; 18 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Published material
  - United American Sculptors first annual exhibition catalog, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Announcements of exhibitions featuring Konzal's work, 1949-1954; 8 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fairfield County Fair flyer, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Announcements of exhibitions featuring Konzal's work, 1955-1961; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Announcements of exhibitions featuring Konzal's work, 1962-1964; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ephemera
  - Correspondence from Konzal to the WPA concerning Konzal's work, 1939; carbon copies; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographic portraits of Konzal, 1950; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Blueprint of a lobby for a modern movie theater produced for the Sculptors Guild, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook, unbound, Undated; photographs, art show announcements, newspaper clippings related to Konzal (Oversize 1)